Guide to the Policy Sciences Center Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Policy Sciences Center records
1948-1987
1968-1974
MS 1882
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
The records include organizational papers, correspondence, financial records, and topical files which document the founding of the Policy Sciences Center in 1948 and its activities over the next thirty years, primarily between 1968 and 1974.
Policy Sciences Center
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Policy Sciences Center, 2006.
Associated Materials
Harold Lasswell Papers (MS 1043). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Organization, 1948-1987. II. Grants, 1968-1978.
Scope and Contents
The Policy Sciences Center Records consist of organizational papers, correspondence, financial records, grant materials, and publications which document the founding of the Policy Sciences Center in 1948 and its activities over the next thirty years. The records are incomplete and primarily highlight the work of the association in the mid-1970s.
The Policy Sciences Center Records were processed as part of a collaborative effort between Manuscripts and Archives and the Yale Law School to document the careers and accomplishments of law school faculty and alumni.
Biographical / Historical
The Policy Sciences Center is a non-profit foundation incorporated in 1948 by Yale Law School faculty members Harold Lasswell, Myres McDougal, and George Dession. The broad mission of the Center was to improve the decision-making process by educating policy makers at all levels. It hosted topical seminars, provided a forum for discussion of topics ranging from juvenile justice to access to capital by minority groups, assisted interested parties in obtaining funds and expertise to perform research, and prepared and reviewed grant applications and reports.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Credit -- United States; Decision making; Endowments; People with disabilities -- Services for; Policy sciences; Brewer, Garry D.; Dession, George H. (George Hathaway), 1905-1955; Lasswell, Harold D. (Harold Dwight), 1902-1978; McDougal, Myres S. (Myres Smith), 1906-1998; Penna, Frank J.; Policy Sciences Center; Yale Law School
- Organization, 1948-1987, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically by subject, the materials in this series focus on financial and membership records of the Center as well as general corporate materials. The series also includes materials collected by Harold Lasswell, one of the original founders.
  - Board of Directors, 1971-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conferences, 1977-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Connecticut, State of, 1948-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Funding, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lasswell, Harold D., 1968-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
  - Membership, 1973-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 7 - 8)
  - Publications, 1972-1973, 1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Report on status of the Policy Sciences Center ("State of the Union"), 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Seminars, 1973-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tax exemption materials, 1966-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 12 - 13)
  - Trademark search, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Grants, 1968-1978, Series II
  The materials in this series relate to grants or projects that the Policy Sciences Center sought funding for either as a direct participant or in its role as a clearing house for interested researchers. The largest amount of materials relate to Garry Brewer's research detailing provision of services to the handicapped in the mid 1970s. Although the documentation for each grant is different, the materials consist primarily of correspondence, applications, and reports.
  - Benoit, Emile, 1975-1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Benton, William (Encyclopedia Britannica), 1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brewer, Garry, 1976-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 3 - 5)
  - Cooperative Action in Food and Agricultural Development, 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fabricant, Neil, 1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Helmick, Raymond (Centre for Human Rights and Responsibilities), 1973-1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Kettering Foundation, 1974-1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 10 - 11)
  - Kutner, Luis (World Habeas Corpus), 1968-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lilly Endowment, 1968-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Mobil Oil Corporation, 1976-1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - National Science Foundation, 1977-1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Office of Economic Opportunity-Minority credit study, 1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Penna, Frank, 1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Snyder, Dick Mershon Center-Ohio State University, 1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Stern, H. Peter (Ralph E. Ogden Foundation), 1968-1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Twentieth Century Fund, 1973-1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - United Nations Institute for Training and Research (UNITAR), 1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - United States Department of Justice, Law Enforcement Assistance Administration, 1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - World Human Rights Advocacy Centers, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Yale University Department of Political Science, 1973, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)